<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short discourse upon the desires of a friend: wherein, upon observation of the late governments and revolutions, it is made evident, what alone can be the perfect settlement of this nation, and the composure of all differences.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3590</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1016_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205202</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864634</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864634</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116866</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93214)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116866)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 150:E1016[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short discourse upon the desires of a friend: wherein, upon observation of the late governments and revolutions, it is made evident, what alone can be the perfect settlement of this nation, and the composure of all differences.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H.H.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 8. 1659"; also the last two numbers of the imprint date have been marked through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116866:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116866:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT DISCOURSE Upon the Deſires of a FRIEND:</p>
            <p>WHEREIN, Vpon Obſervation of the late Governments and Revolutions, it is made evident, What alone can be the perfect Settlement of this Nation, and the Compoſure of all Differences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. H. Anno</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116866:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116866:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A SHORT DISCOURSE</hi> Upon the Deſires of a Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ould I ever deny you any thing, I ſhould now believe it as reaſonable as ever it could be; your queſtions being equally as hard to be determined, as the breaſts of men are to be known: yet, as far as I am able, I will give you my judgment what is the deſigne of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and what will be the neceſſity of all; for it is not now as immediately after the end of the Warre, before deſignes of Self-ambition had been practiſed, and the Nation had not been made wiſe by ſo many cheats; for now, ſucceeding Juglers muſt have the diſadvantage to go about to practiſe thoſe tricks that have been done before. Demonſtration onely makes common people wiſe; and till experimentall feeling gives the ſenſe, profeſſion takes up the place in their opinions. But no new promiſe can now be made to reſtore them their Trade and Freedoms, but it muſt be of ſome of thoſe natures which has been impos'd upon them already; for ſo various have been the Revolutions that have caſt power unto men of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall judgments, that there is little that bears the name of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that has not been reſembled in ſomething lately obey'd. Thoſe two grand Conteſtors for the beſt Government, a <hi>Single Perſon,</hi> or <hi>Many; Monarchy,</hi> or a <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> have both been here practiſed, little to the compoſure of the Nation in Peace and Plenty; whence juſtly may ariſe a Queſtion, What elſe can poſſibly protect, where neither of theſe two can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail; they being, without diſpute, the beſt of others, what ever precedency they have with one another? The Solution of this Queſtion will bring me to anſwer your Demands, I hope, with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116866:3"/>a truth, that I wiſh were convincing to all Mankind, that too great a fondneſſe might be no longer ſhew'd to Power, which always muſt prove as certainly mutable, as it is evidently unjuſt.</p>
            <p>After the end of this Warre, we ſaw, how many ſunck under the temptation of Ambition, when Succeſs gave it a toung to ſpeak; and many without doubt, that ſuſpected no ſuch guilt in themſelves, found it lay concealed from all things but the ſearch of Intereſt and Ambition. I know not where I may fix this modeſt Character upon one, Whether he deſigned as little as the moſt moderate, ſince he reacht at more than the moſt ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; I mean, the firſt Protector, <hi>Oliver,</hi> who wrought himſelf by degrees into power, that he kept almoſt as unexpectedly, as it was unjuſtly gotten; but all things ſo contributed to his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, that he received not leſſe capacity from accidents, than he did from his own abilities. His reputation was higheſt, in the declining time of the Warre; and when he was ready for For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, Fortune appear'd prepared for him; and Victory was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly got whilſt he was amply famous, before time or chance could work any thing to the leſſening of his Reputation; The Nation too was as ready to obey any thing, as he was to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all things; and, wearied with Warre, diſputed not the nicety of a Perſon, but the neceſſity of a Peace; they had yet ſomething left, and fear'd more the effects of a Warre, than the the Uſurpation of Any. Peace and Plenty caus'd the people to be wanton at firſt; Warre and Scarcity, by the ſame reaſon, brought them to be tame at laſt. To enlarge their obedience to him, a victorious Army was at his command; having firſt made himſelf Generall of them, before he attempted to be Prince of others, creeping by degrees into power, and leaving himſelf at a latitude to obey what ſucceſſe offered to him: Thus, as Peace grew ſleighted by long enjoyment, &amp; was the fate of one Man's Power, the want of it now was the life to his; The diſeſteem of Good brought an end to what was Juſt, and the want of the ſame Good gave a beeing to what was Bad; ſhewing, Man neceſſarily muſt be miſerable, unleſſe moderation and firm principles go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern his opinion; that the reall nature of the thing, and not want or enjoyment, makes it more or leſſe.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe Baſes he ſtood, whilſt that which was his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation ſeem'd daily turning to his ruine; The want of a juſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116866:3"/>Title grew chargeable, and the Army grew every day ſenſible they could as well make Power, as preſerve One; and he had no balance upon them but his own ſubtlety. The expectation of the people grew every day leſſe and leſſe anſwer'd; they began to diſcern, that the Charge to maintain an uſurp'd Power was the ſame as the expence of Warre; and the preſervation of ſuch a One needed more Intelligence, and as many Arms, as was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to purchaſe Conqueſt; for the ſame numbers that reacht Victory, were not judg'd enough to preſerve what was gotten, but Militia's in every County were added to the Militia of all the Nation; fain'd Quarrells too, were as neceſſary to keep the Army in peace, as Play-games are to keep children quiet, the Mutiny of the Nation being lookt upon of leſſe conſequence than that of the Souldiery: This employ'd the Navy in Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages to the other World, found out Warre with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> and rendred Peace almoſt as ill-favoured as Warre; their eſteem grown equall by their reſembling charge. Hence a Debt grew contracted, of ſo vaſt a proportion, that the Nation muſt needs tremble at it, who were ſure to be the Pay-maſters: Like the feign'd torments of <hi>Titius,</hi> feeding a Vulture with his own Liver, they fed a gnawing Army with their own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances.</p>
            <p>Whilſt thus evidently every thing was contributing to his fall, the Army beginning to be too wiſe and inſolent, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be too knowing and poor, and he had met occaſions enough during his buſling in Power, to act all his cheats and ſubtleties, which, like Juglers tricks, were not ſo fit to be ſhew'd again, of conſequence the Army appear'd deſigning to be the Judges of all power, the Nation enclin'd to obey none, and he ſinking from the capacity of couſening either, longer.</p>
            <p>Whilſt all things ſeem'd thus ready to contribute to his ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, Fate ſeem'd to prevent that which Fortune deſign'd for him; and that reputation which his life could not long have held up, his death preſerv'd, and by diſſolution liv'd in his ill-coveted fame.</p>
            <p>He left behind him a vaſt contracted Debt, vaſt in it ſelf, though not ſo great, circumſtantially conſider'd, for one to run into, that had an unjuſt Title to maintain, a Nation to couſen, and many Parties to betray; ſo that none needed more Power or Intelligence to preſerve himſelf, and ruine others.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116866:4"/>
Theſe fatal circumſtances he left fix'd to that Throne that his ſon <hi>Richard</hi> was to aſcend, who quickly found that ruine, which perhaps would have been ſlower-pac't to his father; ſince the aſſiſtance that nature and fortune gave to one, was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the other. The father made his ſteps to power by the knowledge of men and victory; the ſon was wholly unpractiz'd in either, to whom the Army had no Obligation; nor was capable of laying any on the Nation. He had never been engag'd ſo much in War as to attempt the one. And his father had left him too poor to perform the other. All he was able to do, was to increaſe the Armies inſolence, by courting them; and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions diſobligation, by paying them: Yet, in the <hi>Parliament</hi> he called, he found a temper exceedingly civil to him; certainly to have preſerv'd him great enough by another, or too great by himſelf; and by ſo publick an endeavour of his preſervation, ſpeedily urg'd on his ruine; rouſing the ſuſpicious Army to put an end to his power, before they knew what to ſet up in his place; that principle ever being prevalent with them, never to like what the Nation would preſerve. This appear'd meerly the raſh reaſon of the Army for what they did; for when they had threatned him ſo fax as to make him diſſolve all his intereſt and honour with the <hi>Parliament,</hi> theſe were ſtill to ſeek what to do, making it evident that the deſtroying part onely, dwelt with Armies; and rendring it as viſible, that the Nations intereſt and theirs were very different, What they did next could not appear the deſign of thoſe neer relations to the Protector that manag'd the injuſtice they offer'd him; and forc'd him to offer others, by doing as much to his power, as they compell'd him to do to the <hi>Parliament's,</hi> making ſhipwrack of their own Soul, and his Honour, in their ſins by the breach of Oaths; in his Crimes, by his breach of Honour. In this giddineſſe, the next object their violent eyes lay'd hold on, was a remnant of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> which before had joyn'd with them in ſuch an injury to the Nations freedom, that the Army could not doubt they would be now leſſe ready for actions of the ſame nature. Theſe people famouſly know by the name of the <hi>Rump,</hi> reſum'd their Seats again by the favour of the mad Souldiery; and preſently made an Order to keep out thoſe Members that they had joyn'd with the Army in ſecluding before, making haſte to ſhew they continued as bad as they had ever been, or as they could now deſire them to be,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116866:4"/>believing it perhaps their onely intereſt to appear to the Army worſe then others, that they might think of imploying none elſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe parcel of Ambitious men, notwithſtanding forgot not their old, fair, and religious pretences, though they could not be ignorant that the people had as little belief for them, as they had real deſigns to merit it. The firſt thing they complain'd of, was the vaſt debt the Protector <hi>Oliver</hi> had contracted; as a ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh to the Government of a ſingle perſon; believing the diſpute was onely between One and Many, when it was indeed onely in matter of Title; being apparent, all Goverment was ill alike that was equally chargeable; which any muſt be, that depended more upon a mercenary force, than a National intereſt. For theſe could not forget, nor was the Nation ignorant, they had been as ill husbands for them before as the <hi>Protector</hi> had been, and could not expect they ſhould be better now, whil'ſt their Title was no better to their power, nor their kindneſſe more to their freedoms, hardly believing thoſe would redreſſe their grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that denied them their lawfull means to have them repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented. Nor had they given ſmall demonſtration what expence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Governours they were, when the Treaſure of all thoſe vaſt Sates was not enough to defray the charge of their Ambitious ruling nor did it ſeem rational that they ſhould condemn a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, for the ſame Crime that their's was ſure to be guilty of. But their policy was only by expectation to keep others quiet till they were ſafe, that none might uſe power till they were faſt in theirs; not caring how many faults the Nation could find in them, when they were render'd too weak to redreſſe them.</p>
            <p>They preſently next made it appear they were ſenſible that the ſervices they received from <hi>Fleetwood</hi> and <hi>Disborow</hi> (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally) was more from accident then inclination, and rewarded them accordingly, giving <hi>Disborow</hi> cauſe to lament his affected roughneſſe and imprudent raſhneſſe, and leaving <hi>Fleetwood</hi> ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid in his old inſenſible eaſineſſe.</p>
            <p>The Army having thus forſaken the <hi>Protector,</hi> they immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call'd in all thoſe Officers that both the <hi>Protectors</hi> had forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Among the reſt <hi>Lambert</hi> appear'd, and in a little while com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded their forces againſt the Riſing in <hi>Cheſhire;</hi> where he gain'd a victory more fatal to himſelf then the worthy Sr. <hi>George Booth,</hi> whoſe ſufferings for a free-<hi>Parliament,</hi> render'd him more ſafe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116866:5"/>than the other was by Conqueſt that fought againſt it. So heavy muſt the Nation's intereſt weigh in any Scales, held by the hand of time.</p>
            <p>The victorious <hi>Lambert</hi> now returning, brought more fears than joy to his Governours; he ſeem'd too great and glorious to obey, unleſſe he were willing: and they doubted his inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to obedience, when ever he believ'd his Commands would be receiv'd: nor durſt they ſtay long from attempting to leſſen him, ſince they doubted not but his abilities, and intereſt in the Army after this ſucceſſe, would make him capable of improving time more then they could do. Judging therefore his power might be more; and their's not encreaſe; they preſently let him ſee what he was to expect, and forc'd him to attempt their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, with the ſame men that had before brought them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: this too with ſome little difficulty he perform'd, and in their places erected a Committee of Safety; every Bear bringing forth a Whelp, that was never to be lick'd into any form.</p>
            <p>The news of theſe alterations came to General <hi>Monck</hi> in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who ſoberly weighing the difference between ſomething like a Government, &amp; that which had no reſemblance to any, and looking perhaps with a prudent eye upon the effects, that the declar'd ſpirit of the Nation would at laſt produce; with a wiſe ſwiftneſſe, and a bold ſpirit, ſuddenly alarm'd his Army: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſnatch't them into a Declaration for himſelf, preſently declar'd his diſſent for what the Army had done in <hi>England,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards whom <hi>Lambert</hi> ſpeedily advanc'd, equally full of error and haſte: and <hi>Portſmouth</hi> preſently after General <hi>Monck,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd alſo, and received ſome of the forc'd-out Members.</p>
            <p>Theſe various Turns a little time produc'd, and ſhew'd the Nation that alike miſery attended the Impoſitions of all Parties, and nothing could be true judges of the way and means to their ſetlement, but their own Repreſentatives, free, and fully choſen: any thing leſſe is but impoſition; and all other pretended paths to ſetlement, are indeed but high-wayes to confuſion, ſince any thing contrary to the Nation's judgement, muſt be chargeable to their purſes. Under the want of the leaſt pretence to this, <hi>Lambert</hi> and his party ſunk, the Nation declining that moſt which had the leaſt ſhew of Government. All theſe things alarm'd that part of the Army that <hi>Lambert</hi> had left behind him in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> who immediatly fell to their ancient cuſtome of undoing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116866:5"/>what they had done, not ſeeming to believe that actions of contrary natures could be blemiſhes to their infallible purity; and preſently drawing together, did invite that parcell of men to ſit again, whom they had forc'd from their Seats before. This act of theirs here in <hi>London</hi> took the ſame impreſſion in the Army under <hi>Lambert</hi>'s command at <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> ſo that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a blow he found himſelf o're-come, and forſaken by all thoſe Troops, which a little before ſeem'd unqueſtionably at his Devotion.</p>
            <p>Thus, freed from a Potent Enemy, Generall <hi>Monck,</hi> victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious without a Conqueſt, marcht towards <hi>London,</hi> receiving from all Counties as he paſt along their Reſolutions, to aſſert their own Right in a Free Parliament; and comming within a day's march of the City, he received from them an Addreſſe of the ſame juſt nature. He was no ſooner come to <hi>White-hall,</hi> but immediately the violent <hi>Rump</hi> prepared an employment of an unheard-of nature for him; which he obey'd, and entered the City, impriſoning ſome of the conſiderable men, throwing down all their Gates, to make them look as ready for ruine as was poſſible, ſo to frighten them into obedience; and ſpread his Tent to the publick view, beholding him gone in to deflowre their Freedoms. Theſe two things the paſſionate <hi>Rump</hi> deſign'd, to render all people they had to do with, either by oppreſſion or odium, uncapable to hurt them, having an equall kindneſſe for him that profeſt their ſervice, and for thoſe that avow'd the contrary, their jealouſies being the true iſſues of their crimes, unlimited to all alike.</p>
            <p>Yet this ſtorm battered not the City's Reſolution, who ſtill continu'd reſolute to keep thoſe poor, that deſign'd to make them miſerable; with whoſe juſt and generous reſolution the Nation comply'd, and it grew preſently diſcernable, how hard it was for any Power to ſubſiſt, upon the dependance onely of an Army's ſtrength, if the Nation did once reſolve to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them by thoſe ſilent wounds, of denying Payments and Taxes of all natures, but ſuch as ſhould be impos'd by all their Repreſentatives. This, with the remembrance of thoſe Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he had received, ſeem'd to waken the Generall, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to his new open'd eyes the ſtrange employment he had undergone, together with the juſt apprehenſions that others of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116866:6"/>the ſame injurious nature would ſuddainly be impos'd upon him, to make him incapable of any thing but their paſſionate commands, by rendring him as infamous as themſelves: Theſe conſiderations perhaps threw him upon treating with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Members; at which alarme, the <hi>Rump</hi> preſently voted the filling up themſelves, but with ſuch Qualifications, that they ſhewd as little kindneſſe to the Nation in their ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to fill up the Houſe, as they did before in their denying to have it enlarged. This unlegitimate Child therefore dyed in its birth, and left none to mourn the loſſe of ſuch a loath'd Iſſue from ſuch hated Parents; and the Secluded Members were now lookt upon as the onely preſent ſhew of Power, that was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in this exigent of time, to act ſome ſuddain relief for the Nation.</p>
            <p>All this while the Generall ſtayed retired in the City, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the reaſons of both ſides, which were with ſo many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages excelling on the Secluded Members part, that aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the danger of ever more truſting the always furious, and now diſoblig'd <hi>Rump,</hi> he permitted them to enter into thoſe places, from whence they had been with-held by force.</p>
            <p>This Proſpect, Sir, I thought fit to give you of things paſt, that you might, by the freſh remembrance of theſe changes, judge of the reaſons I ſhall offer in relation to future Events; it being now ſeemingly probable to gueſſe, what all things muſt center in, though it be impoſſible to judge of man's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; affairs being now as much govern'd by Neceſſity and Exigence, as by Deſigne or Intention. Nor perhaps is there much of either now grounded in many men by right principle, ſince Occaſion every day is ſeen to ſoften men, like Wax, ready to receive the impreſſion of the next Honour or Advantage. The Generall and the Secluded Members are now upon the Stage; and no doubt there are yet mingled with the laſt ſome perſons, ſo wholly wedded to private intereſt and ambition, that they daily endeavour to obſtruct the common advantage, being ſuch as would engroſſe the Sun, not ſhare in its influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; that would ſubject Power to their ſelfiſh Paſſions, and not ſubmit to it reaſonably plac'd, impudently laying their own privat intereſt in one ballance, againſt the Nation's weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the other. The effect of this has already appear'd by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116866:6"/>that every day happen to that haſte that is required to be made, for the determination of this Parliament; and by the harſh and ſplenetive clauſes that are offer'd to be added to every Act and Qualification, it being their intereſt that have alwayes liv'd in bloud to keep all wounds ſtill open. Nor do's leſſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitions and jealouſies attend the General, who ſo darkly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries himſelf, that he rather ſeems to wait upon opportunity then principles, and yet ſeems more affected to his private opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion then the Nations judgement, having declar'd his own, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have given their's. But to how little purpoſe it is, as well as how unjuſt, I hope I ſhall eaſily ſhew you; and I doubt not but it may as eaſily be diſcern'd by any that will conſider (with paſſion laid aſide) the late revolutions I have preſented to you, by which their reaſons may be directed to find the one ly grave to bury all former animoſities and future charges in.</p>
            <p>The diſpute of late years has fondly been concerning what Goverment is beſt, and in this many have engag'd as their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt have led them, and it is very true, it might in reſpect of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their particulars merit the name of a Queſtion; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all thoſe that judge their power and advantages would be greateſt by one or t' other: but admitting nothing to receive any conſideration but the Nations good in general, then it will not ſeem a queſtion, for both have been tried in a reſemblance enough to demonſtrate, that they are equally prejudicial to the Nation's good, for both alike muſt of neceſſity ſupply their want of Title with Armies; and the charge being the ſame, it matters not to diſpute the difference of the impoſers, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being too poor to wait the tedious effect of any pretended good cauſe: nor is it reaſonable to expect good from profeſſion and opinion; when it is ſooner to be compaſs'd by demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and action.</p>
            <p>I call that a true Title that the Nation will judge ſo, for that of conſequence is the beſt, whether by one or many, ſince that Government may venter to depend ſoly upon the National, not the Military intereſt, whereby the Nations charge may be contracted, their Trade reſtor'd, which under a power pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd by force is impoſſible to be, no more then houſe-keeping is to be made leſſe chargeable, and the family ſtill left uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:116866:7"/>
The General cannot but ſee this; If he deſign's to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf great, he muſt ſurely reflect upon the certain ruine he run's into, if he remembers but what ſucceſſe others had in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of it, and how much more faire it ſtood when <hi>Oliver</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector attempted it, than it now do's for him. The reaſons I have laid down before, and in ſhort they are to be thus reduc'd. The Nation is grown wiſer and poorer, and therefore the unlikelier to be couſen'd again, or to be longer fantaſtick. He will diſcern too, he cannot ſubſiſt without power enough to force the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a ſubjection they are not inclin'd to, and he may as well fear he muſt be put to pay them by ſome other means, than out of the purſes of thoſe, he fixes ſlavery and diſcontent on. Next, the uncertainty of Souldiers may ſhake his unjuſt thoughts (if he has any,) and let him ſee he ought not to depend upon a certainer temper in them, than they have alwayes expreſt inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in themſelves. His Army now cannot ſhew greater affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for him, than they themſelves and the other Army have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt to others, and yet have turn'd from all that profeſſion into a violent extream. Laſtly, 'tis evident the Nation's poverty and diſaffection will make him uncapable of rewarding the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations of thoſe that ſhould raiſe him to a deſir'd Greatneſſe: they would ſet ſo vaſt a rate upon their merits, that he muſt be their glorious ſlave, and wear a mingle of Majeſty and Shackles; not daring to command thoſe, whom he is unable to reward; and from natural neceſſity they muſt become the executioners of that power they gave him. All this by experiment and reaſon muſt be viſible to him; unleſſe the temptation of preſent Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition dazels his eyes from ſeeing the future hazards: few men being warned enough by the deſtiny of others; but are ſo fond as to believe that they have kinder Stars then the whole World beſides. I wiſh, this may not be the General's fatal perſwaſion, but that he may perpetually preſerve himſelf in juſt honour, and reaſonable ſafety, anſwering the wiſhes and expectation of the whole Nation; in continuing to defend them, in what they ſhall judge fit for themſelves, and to confider how all previous engagement, of never ſo fair a nature, is but robbing them of that judgement which purely ought to flow from themſelves. Of equal fate and injuſtice it will be for him to perſiſt in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing many Governours: to tender his opinion may reſemble
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116866:7"/>duty, but to ſecond it with force is uſurp'd Dominion: and he will appear equally juſt, and kind, to uſurp Dominion him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or to aſſiſt others in the uſurpation of it, ſince every Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment contrary to the Nations judgement, muſt be as charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in their own defence, as they are unjuſt in their own impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. Nor can ſuch ill men as now perhaps add to his temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations agree long with him, or one another, in the ſharing of power; The modeſty that is found in the purſuit, is loſt in the acquiſition. And late experience is ſeconded by reaſon to aſſure us, that ſuch mens knowledges of one anothers Crimes and Subtilities, divide thoſe plots among themſelves they once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed others by. Like thoſe that roſe together from the earth by the ſown-teeth of Dragons converted preſently their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal malice among one another.</p>
            <p>No Stories has ſhown us precedents of miſchiefs that we have not equall'd in our Revolutions. The <hi>Roman</hi> Army, never made and unmade Emperours faſter, than Ours has ſet up and pull'd down Governments; ſo that a reaſonable man would think it impoſſible, that ever any perſon ſhould be ſo infatuated as wholly to throw himſelf upon them more;or ſo unchriſtian-like as to ſuffer the almoſt-ſhipwrackt Veſſel of the Nation to be yet expoſed to more Army-ſtorms, ſince things are now growing to that Exigence, that the General muſt chuſe ſafety and honor with the Nation, or hazard and uncertain glory with an Army. It being poſſible that an Army may be preſerv'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Nation's Government, but never the Nation under the Armie's.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir, I ſhall give you my judgement of what I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Nation will onely be able to reſton. It will be, To find out ſuch a Government as may compoſe all differences, confirm all ſales, and make Oblivion and Indempnity perfect: and when none ſhall want pardon or ſecurity, there will not be ſo many enemies left, that will put the Nation to maintain ſuch charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able defences for their ruler; That which onely can do this, is the ancient conſtitution of King, Lords, &amp; Commons. For to defend any Uſurper againſt the King's title will be chargeable; to keep him out makes all indempnity imperfect; and none can imagine they ſhall ſafely enjoy their purchaſes, unleſſe they were ſure that no chance, or revolution, ſhall ever throw that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116866:8"/>into his power, which we deny to give him; nor will the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ever be content to pay the Souldiers Arrears, till they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe by it a ſetlement according to their own judgement.</p>
            <p>The King is now fit in all reſpects to be treated with: The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his religion, his being free from engagements with forreign force, unblemiſh'd from any injury he ever did the Nation, may reaſonably aſſure us, that he is both capable to forgive, and would be willing to confirm; rather to make a grave to bury all diſputes, than by ravelling into former actions raiſe new ones; and would certainly be convinc'd that the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of reſtoring all purchas'd Lands, would be over-weigh'd by the neceſsity and juſtice of confirming them; ſince the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by confirmation may be ſooner repaired, then the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice reſtoration will bring. For by ſuch moderate wayes they may be ſetled, that no parties will have cauſe to be griev'd, if all will be content but to ſhare with the whole Nation in ſome dammage.</p>
            <p>And if the Nation makes not themſelves capable thus to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an oblig'd Prince, they will probably admit a victorious One, and be ever wretched under the effects of Conqueſt; he notwithſtanding will be free before God for recovering his rights by ſuch a way, when he is deni'd it by a <hi>Moderator,</hi> and at their doors the ſin will lye, who ſtill deſign the Nation to be their ſlaves, or force them to be ſo unto another, unleſſe his vertue frees them from that condition, which the Crimes of others threw them into.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I have delivered my particular opinion, and I hope there is no man living that owns this Nation for his Countrey, but will ſubmit to the judgement of it, oblig'd to no particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar deſigns by private paſsions, but bound to obey the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe, who onely can determine what is conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for themſelves; ſo that 'tis not the Title of any ſingle man, nor the pretences of many, that ought to be preferr'd before the Nation, or to be impos'd upon the people; nor either of theſe juſtly to be refus'd, if the Nations good ſhall appear to conſiſt with the Government of either. To the free Parliament therefore, let every man appeal, and there indeed he may embrace a certain good cauſe, ſince ſuch a one is ſure to be for his Countrey's good, that wholly reſigns himſelf to their judgements.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116866:8"/>
I hope, Sir, theſe Reaſons will make an impreſsion in your breaſt, and I wiſh it were poſsible they might have the ſame effects on every individual man, that the Nations conſcience and intereſt may at laſt meet, which has been ſo long ſeparated by the ſucceeding ambitions of a few men, nor have I deliver'd you any opinion, which ſhall not be aſſerted, when occaſion requires it, with the life and fortune of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
